Guide to the William Hauptman Papers
The Wittliff Collections
William Hauptman Papers
1954-1993
1975-1993
The Wittliff Collections
Hauptman, William, 1942-
SWWC.051
4 Linear Feet
4 boxes Plus one map drawer folder.
The William Hauptman Collection contains drafts, manuscripts, typescripts, notes, photographs, and correspondence with dates ranging from 1956-1993.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hauptman, 1994.
Biographical Notes
Playwright and novelist William Thornton Hauptman was born November 26, 1942, in Wichita Falls, Texas. As a child in Wichita Falls, Hauptman attended many plays, readings, and magic shows in the large municipal auditorium there, and saw such actors as Charles Laughton and Gene Autry. He graduated from Wichita Falls Senior High School in 1961, and earned a B.F.A. in Drama from the University of Texas in 1966. His undergraduate degree focused on acting; Hauptman did not decide until graduate school that he wanted to pursue playwriting. He completed an MFA in playwriting at Yale University School of Drama in 1973. He then went on to teach playwriting at Adelphi College in Garden City, NY, 1973-75, and at Yale University School of Drama, 1976.
Hauptman is a successful dramatist. He won a Obie Award for Domino Courts/Comanche Café 1978. For Denmark Vesey (1981 PBS teleplay) he won a NAACP Freedom Foundation Award and an Emmy Award nomination. For Big River (1985), a Broadway musical based on Mark Twain's The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, with music written by Roger Miller, he earned a Tony Award for Best Musical Book. For the play Gillette, he won Los Angeles Drama League Award (1986).
His non-stage writing is equally well-recieved.For Good Rockin' Tonight and Other Stories (1986), he received the Jesse Jones Award for Best Fiction by a Texas Author from Texas Institute of Letters.
Hauptman served as Associate Professor at the Texas Center for Writers in 1996, and returned in 2000 to continue teaching. His novel, The Storm Season, originally published by Bantam Books in 1992, was published as a reprint edition by the University of Texas Press in Fall 2000, as part of the Southwestern Writers Collection Series.
Scope and Contents
Drafts, manuscripts, typescripts, notes, photographs, and correspondence comprise this collection, with dates ranging from 1956-1993. The bulk of the collection is comprised of manuscript and typescript drafts of Hauptman's works, mostly his plays and screenplays, with sparse correspondence and publicity. Early works include a 1956 short story titled Wild Life in Canada (1956), complete with drawings of characters. A letter from Hauptman to Roger Miller regarding their collaboration on the award-winning play Big River, is located with the typescript of that play. Of additional note are the poetry, journal entry, and short story which developed into the novel, Storm Season, as well as correspondence from Hauptman to editor Debbie Futter, at Bantam, Doubleday, Dell, regarding, among other things, the title of the novel.
Published works cataloged separately.
Dramatists; Screenwriters -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th century; Hauptman, William, 1942-
- Work, 1954-1993, undated
  Series Description
  Drafts, manuscripts, and typescripts of Hauptman's plays, teleplay, screenplays, short stories, poetry, novel, articles and criticism are located in this series. Titles under each genre are filed alphabetically. Related correspondence, reviews, clippings, publicity, and playbills are filed after the draft or script for each title.
  - Plays, 1972-1986, undated
    - Big River, 1986
      - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence (letter to Roger Miller) (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Domino Courts / Comanche Café
      - Manuscript with drawings (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Playbills (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Durango Flash
      - Typescript, Second draft, with annotations (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gillette
      - Playbill and poster (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Heat, 1972
      - Manuscript / Typescript (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - As published by Samuel French Inc., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Reviews and poster (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Shearwater
      - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Portion published in Performance magazine (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Playbill (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Teleplays, 1981
    - Denmark Vesey (First draft shooting script), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Screenplays, 1992-1993, undated
    - Cody (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Gillette (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Good Rockin' Tonight: Second draft typescript (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Good Rockin' Tonight: Typescript (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Never Never Land (typescript), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Storm Season (typescript), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - There Aint No Such Animal (typescript, based on story by Bill Bret), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Short Stories, 1954-1991, undated
    - "Echo Park", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Good Rockin' Tonight": Typescript, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Good Rockin' Tonight": As published in Playboy magazine, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Good Rockin' Tonight": Reviews, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Holes" (typescript), circa 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Tornado Story" (photocopy of manuscript), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Tornado Story": Tornado Journal (notes regarding development of tornado story), 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Wild Life in Canada", by Hauptman and Frank Joiner, photocopy of manuscript, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Poetry, undated
    - It Is My Brother (poem which became Storm Season) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Monographs, 1992, undated
    - The Storm Season, 1992, undated
      - First draft (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
      - Second draft (Box 3, Folder 14, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - Portion published in Southwest Review (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence with editor Debbie Futter, at Bantam, Doubleday, Dell, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Address re Storm Season (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Dust Jacket art – color copy (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles and Criticism, 1984-1992, undated
    - Articles, 1983-1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Contents
      "They Love Him Tender, Love Him True" New York Times Magazine. August 7, 1988
      "Close Encounters with Tornadoes" Reader's Digest. July 1985
      "Will the World Flock to Wichita Falls?" New York Times Magazine. August 7, 1988
      "The Desert: A Short Story" The Atlantic Monthly. March 1983
      "On the Dryline" The Atlantic Monthly. May 1984
    - Book reviews by Hauptman, 1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Scope and Contents
      Books reviewed:
      Strange Angels by James Agee The Fifties, by David Halberstam Young Men and Fire, by Norman Maclean
- Photographs, 1983, undated
  Color 3.5"x5" snapshots taken and annotated by Hauptman document people (including Hauptman's brother and father), places (including Wichita Falls and the Oklahoma Union Power Plant), and various tornadoes and cloud formations. Includes one 11x14 photograph.
  - Mountain Men Rendezvous (2) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - People (4) - including Hauptman, Tom (brother); Drenan, Willie (father); Brett, Bill; People participating in Hands Across America (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Places (7) - including Wichita Theater, Riverside Cemetery, Abandoned gas station near Olney, Old Magnolia Recovery, Burl's apartment, Medicine Park home, The Holy City (near Lawton) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Power plants (3) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Tornadoes and clouds (13) - including Mammatus clouds, Laminar showers around rotating supercell, Wall cloud, Supercell near Archer City with curtain cloud going into funnel by hidden rainshower, Vernon tornado, 1983, Big merocyclone near Oklahoma Union Power Plant, Blue Norther, Strange Clouds, Roll cloud, Rainbow lensing effect near Graham, Looking up at storm tower of Archer City supercell, Supercell, 1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Artifacts, undated
  This series includes a harmonica owned by Hauptman.
  - Harmonica (Box 4, Folder 15)